<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<XML>
    <title>An exploration of how and why places become invested with SACREDNESS and how the SACRED is embodied or made manifest through <discipline>ART</discipline> and <discipline>ARCHITECTURE</discipline></title>

<header><location build="shrine">ISE SHRINE</location>, <location type="country">JAPAN</location></header>


<p><nature plant="tree">Trees</nature> and <nature type="unanimate">stones</nature> have long been objects of deep devotion in <location country="japan">Japan</location>. Originally there were no <location build="shrine">shrine buildings</location>; instead a <nature plant="tree">tree</nature>, <nature place="forest">forest</nature>, or a <nature type="unanimate">large boulder</nature> or a <nature place="mountain">mountain</nature>, festooned with ropes, would be the focus of worship.</p>

<p>In <location country="japan">Japan</location> the mysterious forces of nature, called ke, were believed to permeate palpable matter and formless space (collectively called mono in <language>Japanese</language>) to create mononoke. Mononoke was seen to coalesce in <nature plant="tree">trees</nature> and <nature type="unanimate">stones</nature>. Certain <nature plant="tree">trees</nature>, especially the <tree>cryptomeria</tree> and the <tree>evergreen sakaki</tree>, were considered sacred for this reason. When one of these <nature plant="tree">trees</nature> was felled and the <material type="natural">wood</material> used in the construction of a <location build="shrine">shrine</location>, this sacred quality was believed to follow it into the <location build="building">building</location>. The sacred <nature plant="tree">tree</nature> itself was literally and symbolically present in the form of a pillar or post around which the <location build="shrine">shrine</location> was constructed.</p>

<p>The great <location build="shrine">Shinto shrine</location> at <location>Ise</location> is built amid a dense <nature place="forest">forest</nature> of giant <tree>cryptomeria</tree> <nature plant="tree">trees</nature> next to the <nature type="water"><location type="landmark">Isuzu River</location></nature> at the foot of <nature type="unanimate"><location type="landmark">Mount Kamiji</location></nature> and <nature type="unanimate"><location type="landmark">Mount Shimaji</location></nature> in the <location type="region">Mie Prefecture</location> [see Mie Prefecture] in <location type="region">southern Honshu</location>, <location type="country">Japan</location>. Crossing the <location type="landmark">Uji Bridge</location> and passing through the large <location type="landmark">torii gate</location> marking the entrance to the <location type="building">shrine</location>, a long path leads to <location type="building">Ise Jingu</location> (Ise Grand Shrine).</p>

<p>The <location type="building">shrine</location> consists of two groups of buildings: the <location type="building">Imperial Shrine</location> (Kotai Jingu), also known as the <location type="building">Naiku</location> (inner shrine), and the <location type="building">Toyouke Shrine</location> (Toyouke Daijingu ) which constitutes the <location type="building">Geku</location> or outer shrine. The <location type="building">Naiku</location> is dedicated to the <people type="deity">Sun Goddess Amaterasu Omikami</people> (Heaven-Illuminating Great Deity), and the <people type="deity">Geku to the Goddess of Cereals Toyouke Omikami</people> (Abundant Food Great Deity). Each <location type="building">shrine</location> is composed of a number of buildings, including <location type="building">ancillary shrines</location>, <location type="building">workshops</location>, <location type="building">storehouses</location>, etc. Each <location type="building">shrine</location> has an inner precinct with a main sanctuary and two <location type="building">attendant shrines</location>, as well as treasuries, fences, and gates.</p>
    
<p>Both <location type="building">shrines</location> are constructed of <material type="natural">wood</material>, and every <time>twenty years</time> both are totally rebuilt on an adjoining site. The empty site of the previous <location type="building">shrine</location> (called the kodenchi) is strewn with <material type="natural">large white pebbles</material>. The only building on the empty site, which retains its sacredness for the intervening <time>twenty years</time>, is a <location type="building">small <material type="natural">wooden</material> shed or hut</location> (oi-ya) inside of which is a post about <measurement type="feet">seven feet high</measurement> <location type="building">known as shin-no-mihashira</location> (literally the august column of the heart, or more freely translated as sacred central post). The new <location type="building">shrine</location> will be erected over and around this post which are the holiest and most mysterious objects in the <location type="building">Ise Shrine</location>. They remain hidden at all times.</p>



<p>The oi-ya in the old <location type="building">shrine</location> compound of the <location type="building">Naiku</location>
[another photograph of the same]
<people type="person">Kenzo Tange</people> and <people type="person">Noboru Kawazoe</people> (p. 167, see Bibliography below) suggest that:</p>

<p>the erection of a single post in the center of a sacred area strewn with <nature type="unanimate">stones</nature> represents the form taken by <people type="nationality">Japanese</people> places of worship in very ancient times; the shin-no-mihashira would thus be the survival of a symbolism from a very pimitive symbolism to the <time>present day</time>.</p>
<p>The present buildings reproduce the temple first ceremoniously rebuilt in <time type="year">692 CE</time> by <people type="person">Empress Jito</people>. The first temple had been built by her husband <people type="person">Emperor Temmu</people> (678-686), the first <title>Mikado</title> to rule over a united <location type="country">Japan</location>.</p>

<p><people type="person">Emperor Temmu</people> had established Ise as the principal cult <location type="building">shrine</location> of Imperial <location type="country">Japan</location>, but the site itself, and the <tree>cryptomeria</tree> <nature plant="tree">trees</nature> that grew on it, were already sacred before then. The <tree>cryptomeria</tree> is a <nature plant="tree">tree</nature> associated with Shinto <location type="building">shrines</location>. The principal sacred plant of <location type="region">Shinto</location>, however, is the <tree>sakaki</tree> (a shrub related to the tea bush). The shin-no-mihashira is taken to represent a branch of the <tree>sakaki</tree> stuck upright in the ground.</p>

<p>The chambers of the <location type="building">shrines</location> are raised on <material type="natural">timber</material> piles which themselves are analogous to the central sacred post. The roof is not supported by the walls (although the rafters do rest on purlins), but the ridge beam is carried instead by two large columns at either end which embedded directly into the ground without any foundation.</p>

<p>Besides <nature plant="tree">trees</nature>, at the <location type="building">Ise Shrine</location> are many subsidiary <location type="building">shrines</location> of <nature type="unanimate">rocks</nature> from the sea which are regarded as the abodes (iwakura or rock abodes) of deities.</p>

<metadata>Bibliography:

Kenzo Tange and Noboru Kawazoe, Ise: Prototype of <people type="nationality">Japanese</people> Architecture, Cambridge, Massachusetts: M.I.T. Press, 1965.
Yasutada Watanabe, Shinto Art: Ise and Izumo Shrines, New York: Weatherhill, 1974 (first published in <people type="nationality">Japanese</people>, 1964).
The Roots of <people type="nationality">Japanese</people> Architecture, a photographic quest by Yukio Futagawa, with text and commentary by Teiji Itoh, New York: Harper &amp; Row, 1963 (first published in <people type="nationality">Japanese</people>, 1962).</metadata>
</XML>